<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tech ramblings by Marcin</title>
    <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tech ramblings by Marcin</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Git - conditional configs and commit signing</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/03/28/git-conditional/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/03/28/git-conditional/</guid>
      <description>Recently I came across two very interesting options in git that I wanted to make a note of.
One is a general feature - conditional configs - that you can probably utilise in a myriad of ways. The second - commit signing - might seem a bit obscure.
Conditional configs It appears it&amp;rsquo;s really easy to put conditional properties into your .gitconfig file. This way, you can have a separate entities depending on which repositories you commit to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Payload after load, really?!</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/02/29/payload-after-load/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/02/29/payload-after-load/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;source: Dall-E, prompt: generate an image for blogpost titled &amp;ldquo;breaking a paywall&amp;rdquo;, about exploiting newssite paywall using browser extension&amp;rdquo;
Today&amp;rsquo;s internet is progressively becoming more and more hostile. It is actually a bunch of walled gardens, in the form of Facebook, Instagram, Linkedin, all the other social media outlets. Now, also news sites are increasingly becoming a payed instances.
I totally get it, authoring all that content is not cheap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>useful CLI tools from other planet</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2023/10/10/useful-cli-tools-from-other-planet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2023/10/10/useful-cli-tools-from-other-planet/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve already written a short post about me using fzf on this blog. And I still use it, it still is awesome! :)
But there are more tools like that. Maybe this is just my optics, but with the recent (at least 2 last years) rust&amp;rsquo;s rise to popularity, there are a lot of small tools doing a single task, or focusing on specific kind of problems. And they of course target terminals!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>git-commit script</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2023/06/27/git-commit-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2023/06/27/git-commit-script/</guid>
      <description>The organization I work in, has this practice of annotating commit messages with ticket numbers. From what I know this tends to be quite a common them all around the IT industry. It serves the purpose of accountability for future checks, current information for others on what the commit is actually about, etc. There may be many more things to add here - as an adventage of such a
Some time ago I&amp;rsquo;ve started using this small snippet of code as my pre-commit hook.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>an ode to fzf</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2023/05/29/an-ode-to-fzf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2023/05/29/an-ode-to-fzf/</guid>
      <description>What is fzf? How could I&amp;rsquo;ve lived without it for so long?! It&amp;rsquo;s just a pretty little fuzzy search tool, written in go. You can find it here: https://github.com/junegunn/fzf
Important features fuzzy search in a list of lines - thanks to that, it&amp;rsquo;s really easy to find something in a considerably big list of items it&amp;rsquo;s blazingly fast! very nice shell integrations many additional features - like preview for files (go here to see examples: https://github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>running gamecube emulator on Linux</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2021/02/07/running-gamecube-on-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2021/02/07/running-gamecube-on-linux/</guid>
      <description>I have a fondness for all the retro things in tech, and try to hone this when I have time with exploring old tech. This time I tried running one of the retro consoles&amp;rsquo; emulators. I chose Nintendo Gamecube - because of many reasons, but one of them being I own a quite recent incarnation of the Nintendo spirit, namely Nintendo Switch. So with the older one I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to see how the games look like back than and how much the landscape of gaming on Nintendo has changed with that big of an age gap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>awesome WM and how to handle multiple monitors</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2021/02/06/awesomewm-multiple-monitors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2021/02/06/awesomewm-multiple-monitors/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve started using new window manager. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to try some kind of tiling window manager I thought that a fresh installation of an OS on a new machine is good time to have a go at that.
From the multitude of possibilities I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen AwesomeWM. It&amp;rsquo;s reasonable enough in its standard configuration so I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to stick with it at least for the time being. In fact the only important feature I look for in a tiling window manager is the tiling behavior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>operating systems showdown</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2020/12/05/operating-systems-showdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2020/12/05/operating-systems-showdown/</guid>
      <description>Modern open source operating systems vs modern software development practices The reason to write this blog post was a presentation I watched some time ago, and commented on it on Twitter:
One of the slides from the presentation. How can you develop an operating system and follow *that* kind of process?! :sadpanda: pic.twitter.com/3XuHMXc0My
&amp;mdash; Marcin Cylke (@zygm0nt) January 5, 2020 So to be specific - the whole presentation was rather negative towards security model used along OpenBSD development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>plotting data availability with matplotlib</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2020/03/13/plotting-with-matplotlib/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2020/03/13/plotting-with-matplotlib/</guid>
      <description>Though somewhat strange I happen to come to a need of having a plot of dates that a particular dataset is available on. Doing my exploration in Jupyter notebook it just felt pretty natural to have it written in Python and generated as a graph, with matplotlib.
This resulted in a visually appealing description of the dataset. Also, due to the ease of change, I could modify the plot to show additional elements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I don&#39;t do backups</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2020/02/26/i-dont-do-backups/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2020/02/26/i-dont-do-backups/</guid>
      <description>I tend to not do backups. I used to but just didn’t like it. I wasn’t diligent enough, didn’t have a routine setup. It all felt fragile and error prone in the end. So I stopped. You probably wonder when this will actually hit me - I sometimes do, too.
But the truth is I do have backups. I just don’t keep them by myself, I delegate.
I use the computer mainly to do web browsing, photo management, programming, exploration.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
