<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conference on Just a blog</title>
    <link>http://marcin.cylke.com.pl/categories/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conference on Just a blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://marcin.cylke.com.pl/categories/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Scalar Conf 2016</title>
      <link>http://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2016/04/29/scalar-conf-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2016/04/29/scalar-conf-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Scalar Conf 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://marcin.cylke.com.pl/assets/POLIN-Museum-of-the-History-of-Polish-Jews-int02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Polin museum - interior&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This small conference had its third installment in (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.polin.pl/en)[Polin&#34;&gt;http://www.polin.pl/en)[Polin&lt;/a&gt; - Museum of the History of Polish Jews]. Organizing Scala conference isn&amp;rsquo;t that obvious and having that kind of attention is really great - all the foreign speakers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a quick recap of presentations I&amp;rsquo;ve attended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;having-a-cake-by-paweł-szulc:dce739b86c0a87e1707117ba023d86a9&#34;&gt;Having a cake &amp;hellip; - by Paweł Szulc&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A keynote about typeclasses. I&amp;rsquo;ve read the slides before the presentation  -and they are available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/paulszulc/introduction-to-type-classes-in-30-min&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, so it wasn&amp;rsquo;t new to me. But I&amp;rsquo;d strongly recommend to watch this talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there is another nice talk by Paweł: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ENtdZ9MBo5Y&#34;&gt; Category theory is absolute general nonsense!&lt;/a&gt; This talk is in Polish only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;eff-monad-by-eric-torreborre:dce739b86c0a87e1707117ba023d86a9&#34;&gt;EFF Monad - by Eric Torreborre&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different way of monadic composition, implemented in a separate library: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/atnos-org/eff-cats&#34;&gt;eff-cats&lt;/a&gt; (there is also scalaz alternative). Technically it was a bit over my head, but after experimenting with the concept at home it seems interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked that Eric, being Zalando employee, developed that for their internal usage. Also the beauty of easily constructing different technological stacks with consistent API is very tempting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting things used/mentioned were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;github.com/non/kind-projector&#34;&gt;non/kind-projector&lt;/a&gt;- for projections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haskell.cs.yale.edu/?post_type=publication&amp;amp;p=319&#34;&gt;Monad Transformers and Modular Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;incremental-compiler-by-krzysztof-romanowski:dce739b86c0a87e1707117ba023d86a9&#34;&gt;Incremental compiler - by Krzysztof Romanowski&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep dive into scalac incremental compiler implementation. While the presentation itself, the way it was presented, was very nice, I didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly enjoy the topic. It seemed more appropriate for tools&amp;rsquo; developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;akka-cluster-with-etcd-by-maciej-biłas:dce739b86c0a87e1707117ba023d86a9&#34;&gt;Akka cluster with Etcd - by Maciej Biłas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one looked promising. Joining multiple exciting technologies seems often that way. Unfortunately it was rather tech preview of Kubernetes app setup rather than Scala presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a bit disappointed, because looking through the sources of the project &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rkrzewski/akka-cluster-etcd&#34;&gt;akka-cluster-etcd&lt;/a&gt; there are lots of things to describe. Kubernetes not being one of them ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shapeless-easy-by-valentin-kasas:dce739b86c0a87e1707117ba023d86a9&#34;&gt;Shapeless? Easy! - by Valentin Kasas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that was a clear introduction to shapeless. Till this presentation I&amp;rsquo;ve treated shapeless as only some vague thingy you use when writing libraries. Valentin proved otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He gave a clear and consistent tutorial on the basics of shapeless and its potential use in some example applications. He created a simple diff tool. Not that useful in real life application, but definitely helped make a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will look into real life examples in near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: The speaker had his presentation in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/marconilanna/REPLesent&#34;&gt;REPLesent&lt;/a&gt;, a sbt plugin for presentations - and performed most of the slide-jumping-fu with just one hand, other held in his pocket :D Looked quite hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valentin also mentioned shapeless&amp;rsquo; typeclass derivation - this actually looks nice! Have a look at this &lt;a href=&#34;https://meta.plasm.us/posts/2015/11/08/type-classes-and-generic-derivation/&#34;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cool-toolz-in-the-scalaz-and-cats-toolboxes-by-jan-pustelnik:dce739b86c0a87e1707117ba023d86a9&#34;&gt;Cool Toolz in the Scalaz and Cats Toolboxes - by Jan Pustelnik&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional Design Patterns - enjoyable talk. With a bit of theoretical background, lots of useful use-cases. The talk was about cats and scalaz - both being very similar, and patterns they contain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functor pattern for abstracting Big Data computations, to achieve easier testability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;composing functors - |@| scream operator - also know (officially) as Applicative Builder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applicative  - a list of computation into a computation of lists, list traversal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applicative pattern for reading config&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is this nice video called &amp;ldquo;A purely functional approach to building large applications&amp;rdquo;. Go see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dS3IlDBDlvo&#34;&gt;it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:dce739b86c0a87e1707117ba023d86a9&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude - the conference was really great. Both the talks and social side of the event were enjoyable. I&amp;rsquo;ve been blown away by the great architecture of the museum itself. Been there a couple times and enjoyed all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much needed change would be to bring more tracks, because sometimes topics were too specific and I&amp;rsquo;d gladly change lecture to some other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the usual conference merch, there were no bags with leaflets and pens etc. It came as a surprise to me, but I also really liked it. People infact throw away most of the contents from such bags. Also, no t-shirt as a default - great idea! If you like it - just buy one, otherwise don&amp;rsquo;t bother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall - great job Softwaremill! Keep up the good work!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lambda Days 2016</title>
      <link>http://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2016/02/20/lambda-days-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2016/02/20/lambda-days-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lambda-days-2016-kraków:7f3feb2c897a8b921f015db0c292ec6c&#34;&gt;Lambda Days 2016 - Kraków&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last two days I&amp;rsquo;ve spend on a conference in Kraków. The topics
revolved around functional programming, with all the experimental stuff,
popular languages, etc. Here are the talks I&amp;rsquo;ve been to and short summaries of those:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-1:7f3feb2c897a8b921f015db0c292ec6c&#34;&gt;Day 1:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Propositions as types&lt;/strong&gt; - the keynote delivered by Philip Wadler - seen it already on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IOiZatlZtGU&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. But the thing with Lambda t-shirt looked funny again :D&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using &amp;ldquo;Program shaping&amp;rdquo; and algorithmic skeletons to parallelise an evolutionary multi-agent system in Erlang&lt;/strong&gt; - pretty long title, huh :) The presentation, thou very academic was also quite interesting. The whole concept not being particularly new, but the set of tools used for refactorings into parallel code seemed interesting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Static analysis to identify divide-and-conquer algorithms&lt;/strong&gt; - how to find particular class of algorithms in existing programs? Interesting but shallow, due to time limitations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Mysteries of Dropbox&lt;/strong&gt; - John Hughes of QuickCheck fame showed how
to test a big system using blackbox approach. Nice presentation, with
all the great insight he always brings into his talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Muvr - Jan Machacek&lt;/strong&gt; - that was a fun presentation. About how to build an app that detects your exercise routine and counts how many repeats you&amp;rsquo;ve done. There&amp;rsquo;ve been all:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spark pipelining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swift code demo (it seemed like Swift IDE offers something similar to notebook-like programming, is it?),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;live coding
Unfortunately due to WiFi&amp;rsquo;s proxy settings the live demo could not be finished, but the code for all this is available somewhere on Github, on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/muvr&#34;&gt;this account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embracing change&lt;/strong&gt; - how to introduce Clojure into your company&amp;rsquo;s
technology stack seamlessly - by &lt;strong&gt;Artur Skowroński.&lt;/strong&gt;
Hilarious presentation about adopting new languages. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t that
groundbreaking, at least for me, but the way it was presented, and the
slides with all the Cthulhu references in them, were great!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-2:7f3feb2c897a8b921f015db0c292ec6c&#34;&gt;Day 2:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things that matter by Bruce Tate&lt;/strong&gt; - great energetic talk, with all the ideas about learning
new languages. Bruce is the author of two excellent books: &amp;ldquo;Seven
languages in seven weeks&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Seven more languages in seven weeks&amp;rdquo; :)
He went through languages mentioned in his books and summed up
principles associated with their inception.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve almost decided to not come to this presentation,
weighting between it and sleeping a little bit longer in my hotel room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Zen of Akka&lt;/strong&gt; - delivered by a resident hakker at Typesafe - Konrad
Malawski. Nice talk about Akka pitfalls, there were lots of
recommendations and even some previously unknown to me features of Akka
toolkit. Plus I loved the Japanese elements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating reactive components using ClojureScript React wrappers&lt;/strong&gt; - by
Konrad Szydlo introduced Rum as a wrapper for React, described part of
the ecosystem and explained mechanics behind the technology. Fine
presentation, very intense on content. Konrad had 111 slides, but
managed to show all of them without being hasty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting started with Frege&lt;/strong&gt; - Lech Glowiak, Frege seems to be a Haskell
on the JVM, which in itself seems like a nice thing. But I treat such
languages rather as nice experiments, than something useful. Especially
its Java interop looks ugly. Nevertheless the presentation was given
from the point of view of language contributor, which Lech is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical demystification of CRDT&lt;/strong&gt; - by Dmitry Ivanov and Nami
Naserazad - both of them from TomTom. Guys are working on TomTom&amp;rsquo;s
NaviCloud product. Their presentation was a practical guide throught the
world of CRDTs (link to wikipedia). They showed their failures in
implementing the system, gave advices, etc. The whole thing is even
uploaded to github, so everyone can check their code
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/ajantis/scala-crdt&#34;&gt;http://github.com/ajantis/scala-crdt&lt;/a&gt;). I&amp;rsquo;ve really enjoyed this talk
due to its technical approach. There were no formal definitions, no
teortical considerations, just clean report from the trenches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purely functiona Web Apps&lt;/strong&gt; - by Michał Płachta - how to write Gitlab
companion app in Haskell + Elm? Haskell for backend and Elm for
frontend. This presentation showed great potential of Elm for frontend
development. Moderatly approachable considering Friday afternoon and my
lack of Haskell knowledge. Still, I plan to come back to this
presentation later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-haven-t-seen-but-plan-to-as-soon-as-videos-are-available:7f3feb2c897a8b921f015db0c292ec6c&#34;&gt;What I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen but plan to as soon as videos are available&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modeling your domain. What have we learned? Where do we go from here?&lt;/strong&gt; - by Norbert Wójtowicz - about modeling domain in Clojurescript apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The F#orce awakend&lt;/strong&gt; - by ewelina Gabasova - F# + geekery, the Twitter
went nuts about that presentation, suppose not without reason&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LFE - a lisp flavour on the Erlang VM&lt;/strong&gt; - by Robert Virding - don&amp;rsquo;t know
why but it seems intriguing enough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:7f3feb2c897a8b921f015db0c292ec6c&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, things you didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be interesting were the best
ones. Highlights being presentations by Bruce Tate, Jan Machacek and guys
from TomTom (Dmitry Ivanov and Nami Naserazad)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to organisers for this conference. But I must say, that day 2 was a lot better than the first one. The talks were better structured and presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea for the organizers - please print the schedule on the back of
conference badge. It was pretty annoying to have to take out the A4
sheets with whole day schedule each time I wanted to look at it&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>