<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Tech ramblings by Marcin</title>
    <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Tech ramblings by Marcin</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Getting things done in a distracted world</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2025/03/13/getting-things-done-in-a-distracted-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2025/03/13/getting-things-done-in-a-distracted-world/</guid>
      <description>Many years ago I&amp;rsquo;ve written somewhat similar piece about navigating all the distractions of my life. You can read it here: https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2016/07/24/it-minimalist/ Years have passed, and I want to revisit the topic. Let this post be a reflection on how my habits changed, but also a summary of techniques that work for me right now.
Let&amp;rsquo;s try to recap my stats for this day, as compared to year 2016 (noted in brackets)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>books I read - Oct - Dec 2024</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2025/01/16/books-i-read-oct-dec-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2025/01/16/books-i-read-oct-dec-2024/</guid>
      <description>Books Book Review: Czysta Ameryka. Przemilczana historia eugeniki by Elizabeth Catte Many interesting observations and a clearly presented opinion on eugenics and its history in the USA. It&amp;rsquo;s quite difficult to get through due to the many facts specific to USA internal politics. It also explores topics loosely connected to eugenics, which may feel tangential but provide a broader context. There is certainly a lot of personal opinions here, referring to the author&amp;rsquo;s hometown.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>books I read - September 2024</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/11/05/books-i-read-september-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/11/05/books-i-read-september-2024/</guid>
      <description>Books Book Review: Stany podzielone Ameryki by Lukasz Pawłowski Written by one of the podcasters from &amp;ldquo;Podcast amerykański,&amp;rdquo; and my great experience with this book was largely due to this connection. The book is fascinating and feels refreshingly objective. Additionally, it offers an insightful analysis of the current state of American society, particularly from a European perspective, providing a unique outsider&amp;rsquo;s view of the country&amp;rsquo;s complexities. Book Review: Persepolis by Marjane Satrapi A classic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Watercolor portrait - made by AI</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/10/04/watercolor-portrait-made-by-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/10/04/watercolor-portrait-made-by-ai/</guid>
      <description>&amp;nbspAn example illustration This article is inspired by a post I&amp;rsquo;ve stumbled upon on LinkedIn, by Guido Appenzeller
Below you can find a reinterpretation of his post. With added details here, and there. The reason for that, is twofold - a) I really like the workflow, b) the original post is missing some details for a first-time user of those tools.
Flux is incredibly good to generate profile pictures, for example this Watercolor one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convenient search in my Obsidian notes</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/09/24/convenient-search-in-my-obsidian-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/09/24/convenient-search-in-my-obsidian-notes/</guid>
      <description>I came across this idea of better search in Obsidian notes: https://simplyexplained.com/blog/how-i-use-alfred-to-search-obsidian-notes/
This should work nicely, but:
it would require installing an additional tool Alfred, would bind even more to MacOS ecosystem - what if I want to use the same workflow on Linux, would not be too VCS friendly - hard to version those UI wizards So I&amp;rsquo;ve figured I can do better, with just CLI tools. That resulted in the following short script:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Youtube video - generate summary</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/09/17/youtube-video-generate-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/09/17/youtube-video-generate-summary/</guid>
      <description>&amp;nbspAn influencer cooking a meal I really like watching some culinary channels on Youtube. Those can be roughly divided into two categories:
people cooking some specific recipe people doing a review of a restaurant or a bunch of them It&amp;rsquo;s nice to watch, but after that not too much I can keep from that. If I like a specific recipe, and I&amp;rsquo;d like to cook that think it&amp;rsquo;s really counter productive to try cooking from the video.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extracting articles from Pocket - or ChatGPT for the needed but not interesting stuff</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/08/26/extracting-articles-from-pocket-or-chatgpt-for-the-needed-but-not-interesting-stuff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/08/26/extracting-articles-from-pocket-or-chatgpt-for-the-needed-but-not-interesting-stuff/</guid>
      <description>Pocket is a nice service. It can save articles from the web for you to read later. Nice. It can even help in bypassing annoying paywalls (more on this here). With the ease of using it, I can quickly end up with a substantial backlog of articles to go through. Since reading long articles on a screen feels like a chore, I came up with the idea of exporting articles into EPub format and reading them on an e-reader.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracers in the dark</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/08/08/tracers-in-the-dark/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/08/08/tracers-in-the-dark/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: This blogpost is not about a specific book, titled Tracers in the Dark: The Global Hunt for the Crime Lords of Cryptocurrency. It&amp;rsquo;s just about execution traces.
I wanted to explore a few techniques for visualising inter-dependencies between fragments of code, modules, etc. Say, you have multiple functions and you want to get some bearing on how much each execution of each of those functions takes. Or you have a complicated system, and you&amp;rsquo;d like to plot remote calls in this system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get to your AWS host with ease</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/06/27/get-to-your-aws-host-with-ease/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/06/27/get-to-your-aws-host-with-ease/</guid>
      <description>If you deploy to cloud, ideally you should be able to analyze and debug your system using observability tools. There should be no need to log in to your hosts directly. But life is life, and there might be issues with this or that, and to debug them, direct access to a host is just much easier.
Instead of doing a long sequence of clicks through your WebUI in AWS console, you can also access your host with a script.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Google Takeout is sooo bad!</title>
      <link>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/06/16/why-google-takeout-is-sooo-bad/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcin.cylke.com.pl/2024/06/16/why-google-takeout-is-sooo-bad/</guid>
      <description>Author: IdeogramAI Prompt: The image shows a typical Google Takeout interface with a large error message indicating that the service is unavailable. In the background, there are frustrated users trying to download their data with unsuccessful attempts, represented by repeated &amp;ldquo;Failed&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Retry&amp;rdquo; notifications.
My current data setup is centered around Google Cloud as a place where I store my data. That&amp;rsquo;s also related to how I use the whole vendor ecosystem.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
